Privacy policy for customer accounts
====================================

The privacy policy for customer accounts supplements the general bahn.de/bahn.com [privacy policy](https://www.bahn.com/en/privacy). 

This notice describes what personal data we process in connection with customer accounts and how you can opt out of this data processing.

### Who is responsible for collecting and processing data?

When you use your customer account, the DB companies DB Vertrieb GmbH, DB Fernverkehr AG and DB Regio AG process your data as joint controllers. The companies have agreed which of them is responsible for privacy-related obligations. The essence of this agreement can be found in this privacy statement.

If you have any questions or suggestions regarding this privacy policy, simply contact one of the DB companies.

DB Vertrieb GmbH  
Europa-Allee 78- 84  
60486 Frankfurt  
Germany  

DB Fernverkehr AG  
Europa-Allee 78- 84  
60486 Frankfurt  
Germany  

DB Regio AG  
Europa-Allee 70-76  
60486 Frankfurt  
Germany  

Ms Dr. Marein Müller is the designated privacy officer for all three companies.

Further information about the customer account are available in the [terms and conditions of use for customer accounts](https://www.bahn.com/en/terms-of-use/customer-accounts-terms-of-use).

### What data do we collect and how and why do we process your data in connection with your customer account?

The aforementioned companies have formally agreed which of them performs a given task as part of this joint processing The key features of this agreement are described below.

**DB Vertrieb GmbH is responsible for the following:**

* Payment processing in connection with sales services and objections handling 
* Credit assessment and fraud prevention measures 

**DB Fernverkehr AG is responsible for the following:** 

* Provision, operation and fault management of the sales infrastructure
* Loyalty programme (BahnBonus)
* Sale of long-distance tickets, including digital provision, as well as ordering and sale of BahnCard and BahnBonus 
* Marketing, communication and customer care 
* Carrying out statistical analyses 

**DB Vertrieb GmbH and DB Regio AG are responsible for the following.**

* Writing to customers (e.g. subscription customers) and advertising measures
* Regional offers

**DB Vertrieb GmbH, DB Fernverkehr AG and DB Regio AG are responsible for the following.**

* Use of websites and apps for the sale of products and services, and the provision of information for marketing communications
* Processes on the train (e.g. ticket sales and inspection, penalty fares)
* Processing and paying ex-gratia settlement and compensation (e.g. due to disruptions and unforeseen events)
* Implementation of data subject rights, complaint management, service concerns and customer dialogue

We collect and process your customer account data exclusively for specific purposes. These purposes may be due to technical necessity, contractual obligations or express requests on the part of users.

Processing personal data in connection with your customer account is based on Article 6(1)(b) GDPR. This also applies to processing that is required in order to take steps prior to entering into the contract , e.g. in cases of inquiries regarding our products or services.

Insofar that we obtain your consent for the processing of personal data (i.e. if you subscribe to our newsletter or use the remain-logged-in option), this consent shall serve as the legal basis according to Article 6(1)(a)) GDPR.

If we are subject to a legal obligation that requires us to process personal data, for example to fulfil tax obligations, this processing shall be based on Article 6(1)(c)) GDPR.

We would like to use your previous and current usage patterns regarding your customer account to provide you with customised contents that will make our range of products more interesting to you as a user. For this we store and analyse pseudonymised usage data from online activities. We can then offer you special advantages such as ticket price reductions and free seat reservations the next time you book a ticket. The legal basis for this is Article 6 (1) (f) GDPR.  
The following contains a more detailed description of the data processing activities that take place when you register for and use a customer account.

List of specific examples:

**Creating a customer account**  
The following mandatory information is required when users create a customer account:

* User name (e-mail address) and password
* First name and surname

It is not possible to create a personal account without supplying this information. All other personal information and details pertaining to the user's travel profile are optional. We save your booking and login data in your customer account and use it for performing internal analyses and marketing research. 

**Booking a digital ticket**      
When you book a digital ticket, our system uses the address details as well as surname and first name in your customer account. In addition, when you book an international ticket via international-bahn.de/bahn.com or certain regional offerings, our system uses the date of birth in your customer account, if you have included it. When the tickets are inspected on board the train, the train attendant's mobile terminal will display the information contained in the ticket.

**Purchasing a BahnCard**  
When you purchase a BahnCard, our system uses the contact and identification data in your customer account. Further information on data processing in connection with the BahnCard can be found at [db-vertrieb.com/datenschutz.](https://www.db-vertrieb.com/datenschutz.)(german only)

**Payment details in customer accounts**  
We process your payment details when handling transactions, such as when you buy a product via bahn.de/bahn.com. Depending on the payment method chosen, we may forward your payment details to a third party, as we work with partner companies in order to process certain payment options. You can use the payment services of PayPal and giropay without payment details being stored in your customer account. 

* **Registration for payment by SEPA direct debit**  
    When you register to use the SEPA direct debit process, you provide us with a SEPA mandate that we can use to deduct payments from your bank account by means of a SEPA direct debit if you have selected this payment option. The legal basis for this is Article 6(1)(b) GDPR.  
     
* **Online activation of the SEPA Direct Debit Scheme**  
    For secure payment with the SEPA Direct Debit Scheme, we provide you with methods for online verification of account access via OpenBanking through Tink Germany GmbH (Gottfried-Keller-Straße 33, 81245 Munich) or Verimi GmbH (Oranienstraße 91, 10969 Berlin) or online identity verification through Verimi GmbH. Depending on which verification method you choose, your personal data (the bank details, name and email address you provided) will be transmitted to the service provider under your instructions. In the automatically opening dialogue of the service provider you will be guided through the selected function and informed about every single step of the data processing. As soon as you have successfully completed the check, you can pay by direct debit. Both service providers act independently as responsible parties. Verimi GmbH will offer you the use of your Verimi customer account, if available, or the creation of a new customer account that will later also assist you with other identity verification procedures. Tink Germany GmbH and Verimi GmbH are authorised account information services that also work for banks and only process your data for the few minutes of the account access check.  
    Further information is also available in the privacy statement in the dialogue window of the respective provider.

* **Payment by credit card**  
    To ensure that your payments are processed securely, payment-related data (amount, booking reference, booking description, payer) in your customer account is forwarded to a payment service provider. The legal basis for this is Article 6(1)(b) GDPR. Our payment service provider for processing credit card payments is PAYONE GmbH, Lyoner Strasse 9, 60528 Frankfurt am Main, Germany. To learn how Payone processes your data, please read its privacy policy at [https://www.payone.com/dsgvo](https://www.payone.com/dsgvo)/.    
    The payment service provider performs the following: processing of credit card data in order to perform payments and store details in your customer account; application of security measures used by your card's issuer (such as 3D Secure and strong customer authentication). No other institution handles your data. We do not receive access to your full credit card data. Instead, we merely save a reference in the form of an abbreviated credit card number so that you can identify it. To prevent cases of fraud, a processor is used to process your device or browser fingerprint along with your payment-related data. This serves to protect you and us by preventing the misuse of your financial details when making payments via bahn.de/bahn.com. The legal basis for this is Article 6 (1) (f) GDPR.

**Enquiry regarding bookings**  
If you use the contact form / chatbot to ask questions regarding a booking, our system uses the details in your customer account, including the contact details it contains, to process your enquiry and in the event of follow-up questions. 

**Offers relating to similar products or services**  
We take steps in order to maintain customer relations with you and to provide you with information and offers which we think will correspond to your travel preferences and interests. We therefore process your data on the basis of Article 6(1)(f) GDPR (plus with the help of service providers) in order to send you information and offers. We use your contact data (name, address and e-mail address which we have received as a result of our business relationship with you) for advertising by post and for similar goods or services by e-mail, in particular for market research, unless you object to such use.

You can object at any time to the future use of your data for such advertising purposes without incurring costs other than those for your internet connection, which you need for communicating with us. Simply send your objection by e-mail to [p.d-datenschutz@deutschebahn.com](mailto:p.d-datenschutz@deutschebahn.com?subject=advertising%20opt-out) or by post to of the above-named DB companies (advertising opt-out).

**Ordering subscriptions online**  
When you purchase a season ticket as a subscription, our system uses the contact and payment data in your customer account. Depending on the offer, identification data such as date of birth or a photograph may also be required. Your customer account displays your current subscription.

**Newsletter registration**  
If you use your customer account to register for a newsletter, our system uses the relevant data in your account.  
When you register for a newsletter, we also store the IP address assigned by the Internet Service Provider (ISP) to your end-user device used at the time of registration, as well as the date and time of registration. The collection of this data is necessary in order to trace (possible) subsequent misuse of the e-mail address of the person concerned and it therefore serves our legal protection. We want to be able to provide you with information that is relevant to you, so we analyse your interest in the contents of the newsletter based on clicks and the display of content via customised links. You can unsubscribe from the newsletter at any time by clicking the relevant link at the bottom of the newsletter. 

**Participating in competitions**  
When we run competitions, we collect data for managing the process. The precise details, i.e. what data is collected and for what purpose, are available on the web page of the relevant competition.

**Virtual chat assistants**  
Virtual chat assistants (also known as chatbots) are used on bahn.de/bahn.com. They are part of our sales channel and help you find information on bahn.de/bahn.com and in the DB Navigator app. They are familiar with our websites' contents and provide keyword-based answers to customers' questions, recommend links to relevant websites or suggest using a different channel if they want to contact us.

We are constantly upgrading our chatbots, which help website and app users to navigate our website and mobile services. At the moment, they cannot process queries about specific contract-related issues. Anyone who has questions of this type can continue to contact us via live chat, phone or e-mail. Users should not provide any personal information when interacting with chatbots.

Our chatbots store customers' queries for a maximum of 34 days so their self-learning feature can optimise how they operate. The chatbot does not evaluate personal data. Usage-related metrics like chat duration, message timestamps, number of dialogues and users’ approximate location are stored only for statistical purposes. We process user information only in order to handle their queries and for internal purposes, e.g. managing and improving processes related to our business and services.

**Booking a digital ticket after visiting a partner website (as part of affiliate marketing activities)**  
If you make a booking on an external partner website after clicking a DB affiliate advertisement, the business partner's cookies on that website are read. The relevant cookies have a lifetime of 30 days. This step is necessary for paying the business partner for the booking you make. We work with the Awin network for the purposes of affiliate marketing. 

### Is my data shared with other parties?

Contract processing generally requires the involvement of data processors who are subject to our instructions, such as e.g. computer centre operators, printing or mail-order service providers, or other agents involved in contractual performance.

External service providers who process data on our behalf are carefully selected and placed under strict contractual obligations. The service providers work in accordance with our instructions. This compliance is verified by technical and organisational measures and supplementary checks.

In addition, we only disclose your data when you have given us your express consent or where we are under a statutory obligation to do so. Transmission to third countries outside the EU/EEA or to an international organisation will not take place unless we have been given reasonable guarantees. These include the EU standard contractual clauses and an adequacy decision by the EU Commission. For example, we may be required to forward data in the following circumstances for the purpose of contract processing when users book services on bahn.de/bahn.com:

* Purchase of travel insurance
* Purchase of hotel services
* Use of the car rental service
* When making use of services for travellers with reduced mobility, your data is sent to the appropriate DB Group offices.
* Credit check when registering for the direct debit procedure by Experian Solutions GmbH
* In the case of payment irregularities or payment default, details of the account receivable may be sent to a debt collection agency.

You purchase our partners' services on bahn.de/bahn.com directly from these partner companies. Further information on this is available under "Do you incorporate data from third parties?"

### How long is your customer account data stored?

We only store your data for as long as necessary so we can achieve the purpose for which it was collected (e.g. in the context of a contractual relationship) or insofar as permitted by law. Thus, in the context of a contractual relationship, we store your data until final completion of the contract. Thereafter, the data will be stored for the statutory storage period.

Your access to your customer account will be automatically suspended following 24 months of inactivity.

### Are cookies used for the customer account?

Cookies are set when you visit your account. The following cookies are also set when you use your account.  
  
**CrossEngage**  
If you have a bahn.de/bahn.com customer account, personal offers and promotions can be displayed when you are logged in. In order to design and display this content, we have to place a cookie on your browser when you use bahn.de/bahn.com. It has a lifetime of 12 months. The data collected via the cookie is pseudonymised and processed on servers of our service provider CrossEngage GmbH (Bertha-Benz-Str. 5, 10557 Berlin, Germany). The legal basis for this is Art. 25 (2) (2) of the German Telecommunication and Telemedia Data and Privacy Protection Act (_Gesetz über den Datenschutz und den Schutz der Privatsphäre in der Telekommunikation und bei Telemedien_, “TTDSG”) in conjunction with Art. 6 (1) (b) GDPR.

#### Cookies that are not essential for using the website:

The following cookies are not essential for using the website and will be processed only if you give your consent beforehand. 

**Remain-logged-in option**   
If you use the remain-logged-in option, you will be recognised and addressed by your name the next time you visit. This allows you to reach certain contents of your customer account more quickly. Use of the remain-logged-in option does not enable direct access to your personal customer account. In order to access your data, such as your address, account or booking information or personal offers, you must always log into your customer account with your user name and password. When you log in, your user name will be pre-entered on bahn.de/bahn.com. By doing so, we aim to provide a faster and more convenient login. We will never pre-enter your password. If your end-user device is used by several people, please make sure that the auto-fill option in your browser is switched off in order to avoid misuse.

**Registration**   
If you wish to use the remain logged in option, we need your consent in accordance with Article 6 (1) (a) GDPR. You can give your consent to the remain-logged-in option upon registration and when logging in to your customer account. By entering your user name and password, ticking the remain-logged-in box and clicking the login button, you consent to the option. You have to give your consent for every end-user device and every browser used. Following your consent, we place two cookies on your browser. These are first-party cookies that can only be read by us. The other cookie indicates whether the remain-logged-in option has been set in your browser. In this case, a randomly generated cookie ID is stored in the second cookie and assigned to your customer account in our system. This only takes place by way of encrypted connections.  
Both cookies thereby enable us to recognise you on subsequent visits to bahn.de/bahn.com and to address you by your name. These cookies are not used to collect usage data from your browser or to link this usage data with data from other browser sessions.  
The cookies for the remain-logged-in option have a lifetime of 24 months. After every login to your user account with your customer name and password, the lifetime of the cookies will be extended by a further 24 months as from this login. 

**Opt out**  
You can opt out of the remain-logged-in option via the link "You are not \[Vorname\]\[Nachname\]? Opt out". You will find the link by clicking on your name, which is displayed on the website. In addition, in your customer account on the "Change login data" page, you can opt out, in a single step, of the remain-logged-in option on all browsers or end-user devices on which you gave consent. This opt-out option is only displayed in the customer account, however, if consent to the remain-logged-in option was given on at least one end-user device.  
If you delete the cookies on your browser, you will also opt out of the option. If a third party uses your end-user device (browser) and logs in to his/her customer account, the remain-logged-in option will also be deleted. 

### What rights to customer account users have?

* You can request information to find out if and what information is stored about you.
* You can request the correction, deletion and restriction of the processing (blocking) of your personal data as long as this is legally permissible and possible within the framework of an existing contractual relationship.
* You have the right to file complaints with the supervisory authority. The supervisory authority responsible for DB Vertrieb GmbH is Der Hessische Beauftragte für Datenschutz und Informationsfreiheit, Gustav-Stresemann-Ring 1, 65189 Wiesbaden, Germany 
* You have the right to the transferability of the data that you have submitted to us based on consent or under a contract (data transferability).
* If you have given us your consent to data processing, you can withdraw it at any time by the same means by which it was given. Withdrawal of consent does not affect the legitimacy of processing carried out on the basis of consent prior to its withdrawal.
* You can object to data processing for reasons arising from your particular circumstances if the data processing is based on our legitimate interests.
* You can opt out of advertising messages at any time with future effect (advertising opt-out).    

DB Vertrieb, DB Fernverkehr and DB Regio share joint responsibility as per Article 26 GDPR. As part of this agreement, the companies have identified which GDPR-related obligations each of them must to meet. Independently of this, you can assert your rights vis-a-vis the above-named companies whenever necessary.   
To exercise your rights relating to your customer account, simply contact us at the following address:

DB Vertrieb GmbHEuropa-Allee 78-84  
60486 Frankfurt   
Germany  
or send an e-mail to [p.d-datenschutz@deutschebahn.com](mailto:p.d-datenschutz@deutschebahn.com).

If you contact one company but another company is responsible for your particular issue, we will forward your communication to the relevant party.

### How up-to-date is this data privacy information regarding the customer account?

We update our privacy notice to bring it into line with new functionalities or legal requirements. We therefore recommend that you check the notice at regular intervals. 

Last updated: April 2023
